{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>This man signed a deed in which Philip Ford gained control of his territories.</em> He limited capital punishment to murder and treason in the Frame of Government. According to tradition, this man promised, under the Great Elm, \u201cperpetual friendship\u201d with the Lenni Lenape at Shackamaxon. He laid out 5 public squares for a city between the Schuylkill (pr. <b>\"school\" \"kill</b>\") and Delaware Rivers. For 10 points, name this Quaker who founded a namesake colony containing Philadelphia.", "answer": "William <b><u>Penn</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em>At a 2015 sporting event in this country, Iranian women unveiled a banner depicting a woman</em> <em>who was arrested for trying to enter a volleyball match.</em> The 2014 G20 Summit was held in this country. Following that summit, several world leaders\u2019 personal details were leaked to the organizers of the 2015 Asian Cup, which took place in this country. For 10 points, name this country where security was tightened following a December 2014 hostage-taking in Sydney.", "answer": "Commonwealth of <b><u>Australia</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>This product was stored in a large container found in the grave of the Lady of Vix.</em> Domitian ordered that Italian production of this good be cut in half. This product was flung at a wall in a game called kottabos. This product was kept in kraters for use during symposiums. Pliny the Elder coined a phrase claiming that there is truth in this substance. For 10 point, name this commodity popular in ancient Greece and Rome which is made from fermented grapes.", "answer": "<b><u>wine</u></b> [or <b><u>vinum</u></b>; or in <b><u>vino</u></b> veritas; prompt on \"alcohol\"; prompt on \"grapes\"]  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>A controversy surrounding this substance led to the Kefauver-Harris Amendment.</em> This substance was promoted by Chemie Grunenthal, and is used in Brazil to treat leprosy. This substance is composed of two enantiomers, one of which is responsible for adverse effects like phocomelia. This substance was meant to treat morning sickness in pregnant women. For 10 points, name this drug that caused a surge in birth defects in the late 1950s and early 1960s.", "answer": "<b><u>Thalidomide</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>A part of this building lent its name to the 1839 Supreme Edict of the Rose Chamber.</em> This place's name literally means \"gate of cannons.\" The head of a regime often called the \"Sublime Porte\" primarily used this building, which contains G\u00fclhane Park. After a 1574 fire, the architect Sinan helped rebuild this four-courtyard building complex, which sits on a hill called Seraglio Point. For 10 points, name this Istanbul building, the primary residential palace of the Ottoman sultan.", "answer": "<b><u>Topkapi</u></b> Palace (\"TAWP-kuh-puh\")  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em>Governor \"Pappy\" O'Daniel was the only man to beat this person in a race for elected office</em>. This man used a helicopter called the \"City Windmill\" to take on Coke Stevenson in one race. John Connally was this man's campaign manager in a race that he won by 87 votes, giving him the nickname \"Landslide.\" For 10 points, name this man who won a controversial 1948 Senate primary race in Texas years before he became President of the United States.", "answer": "Lyndon Baines <b><u>Johnson</u></b> [or <b><u>LBJ</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This man\u2019s first major project was called the Grand Cross</em>. This man\u2019s immediate boss was the Duke of Persigny. Visits to London led this man to build many public parks and botanical gardens, including the Boulogne Woods. This man\u2019s widening of streets was allegedly intended to make it difficult for rebels to set up barricades. For 10 points name this French baron who created many open boulevards during his redesign of Paris in the 1850\u2019s and 60\u2019s.", "answer": "Baron Georges-Eugene <b><u>Haussman</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "BA"}, {"question": "<em>The first of these measures was the third of a set of resolutions introduced by Henry Pinckney.</em> This resolution resulted in the censuring of Joshua Giddings due to the Creole case, and it became a standing rule with the passage of the Twenty-first Rule. John Quincy Adams finally secured the 1844 repeal of this measure, which immediately tabled certain documents. For 10 points, name this Congressional rule which barred the introduction of petitions related to slavery.", "answer": "<b><u>Gag</u></b> Rule  {III}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em>This athlete fleshed out his political viewpoints in the book I Have Changed.</em> This athlete's endorsement of Adidas founder Adi Dassler's shoes helped jumpstart that company. He was forced to ride a freight elevator to a reception in his honor at the Waldorf-Astoria Hotel. This athlete denied that Adolf Hitler chose to snub him. For 10 points, name this African American who won four gold medals at the 1936 Berlin Summer Olympics.", "answer": "James \u201cJesse\u201d <b><u>Owens</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>Angela Davis claimed that this woman wanted \"to exterminate the Negro population.\"</em> She founded a newsletter called <em>The Woman Rebel</em>, whose slogan was \"No Gods, No Masters.\" This person wrote a regular column called \"What Every Girl Should Know\" for a New York newspaper. This woman founded the group that evolved into Planned Parenthood. For 10 points, name this woman who opened the first birth control clinic in the United States.", "answer": "Margaret <b><u>Sanger</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>The \"red\" city of Cleopolis is run by this literary figure.</em> In the original plan for an unfinished poem, this person was to hold a twelve-day feast. This largely-unseen character is the boss of Sir Guyon, who smashes the Bower of Bliss. Prince Arthur has a full vision of this leader, who sends a warrior to defeat a dragon threatening the parents of Una. For 10 points, name this analogue of Queen Elizabeth I whom the Redcrosse Knight serves in Edmund Spenser's <em>The Faerie Queene.</em>", "answer": "<b><u>Gloriana</u></b> [or <b><u>Gloriane</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>Faerie Queene</u></b> before \"<em>Faerie</em>\"; do not accept \"Elizabeth I\"]  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em>This sect initiated clerics through its only sacrament, called consolamentum.</em> The highest rank in this sect was called \u201cparfait\u201d and required strict vegetarianism. Their theology, perhaps inspired by the earlier Paulicians and Bogomils, held that the physical world was evil and created by Satan. Raymond of Toulouse was among the nobles to seize land when Innocent III declared a crusade against them. For 10 points, name this dualistic Christian sect of southern France.", "answer": "<b><u>Cathars</u></b> or <b><u>Albigensians</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "BA"}, {"question": "<em>After this king\u2019s dying wife asked him to remarry, he responded \u201cNo, I will have mistresses!\u201d</em>This king\u2019s wife Caroline of Ansbach was a supporter of Robert Walpole, who served as Prime Minister for the first 15 years of this man\u2019s reign. His son the Duke of Cumberland defeated Bonnie Prince Charlie at Culloden and he was the last British monarch to lead forces in battle.  For 10 points, which Hanoverian king of Great Britain ruled during the Seven Years War?", "answer": "<b><u>George II</u></b> of Great Britain", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>In one trial, this man was defended by George Williams and prosecuted by no one.</em> An action against this man was justified in a letter by Edward Bates. George Cadwalader detained this man under suspicion of raising arms for rebellion against the Union, which led to the unsuccessful intervention by the sitting Chief Justice. For 10 points, name this Maryland man whose right of <em>habeus corpus</em> was the center of a writ issued by Roger Taney.", "answer": "John <b><u>Merryman</u></b> [accept Ex Parte <b><u>Merryman</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>Following one defeat, corpses of these people were looted for items to send back \"to the ladies</em> <em>of Tennessee.\"</em> At a climactic battle, John Coffee's forces prevented this tribe from escaping via the Tallapoosa River. This tribe lost a war that had begun with the Battle of Burnt Corn. Following Menawa's defeat, their chief William Weatherford surrendered at Fort Jackson. For 10 points, name this tribe of what's now Alabama whose Red Stick faction lost at Horseshoe Bend to Andrew Jackson.", "answer": "<b><u>Creek</u></b> tribe [or <b><u>Muscogee</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This band is the main focus of a film featuring a clip of Jefferson Airplane singer Marty Balin</em> <em>getting knocked out</em>. During a performance by this band, Meredith Hunter was killed by the Hell\u2019s Angels who were working security. Its disastrous performance at the 1969 Altamont Free Concert is the subject of the documentary <em>Gimme Shelter</em>, which has footage of them performing \"Sympathy for the Devil.\"For 10 points, name this rock band led by Mick Jagger.", "answer": "The Rolling <b><u>Stones</u> </b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<em>One participant in this event called a different participant \u201chalf militarist half gangster.\u201d</em> The instigators of this event vowed not to pass a poisoned chalice to the defendants, who would be judged by Francis Biddle. This event was criticized by Harlan Fiske Stone as a \u201clynching party.\u201d This event was authorized by the London Charter and led to the death of Hermann Goering and others. For 10 points, name this tribunal which tried leading Nazis for war crimes.", "answer": "<b><u>Nuremburg</u></b> trials", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>One leader of this people won a battle after tossing away his helmet and charging the enemy,</em> <em>shouting \u201cOh my Islam!\u201d</em> These people were led by Aybak, who married Sultana Shajar al-Durr. They revolted against the Ayyubid dynasty and fought a battle where Kitbuqa was defeated by Qutuz. These people stopped the invasion of the Golden Horde at the Battle of Ain Jalut after Hulegu was recalled home. For 10 points, name these former slaves who ruled Egypt.", "answer": "<b><u>Mamluks</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>The creation of this doctrine was spurred by concerns about a phenomenon called</em> <em>\"declension.\"</em> This doctrine amended Chapter XII of the Cambridge Platform and was championed by Solomon Stoddard. This doctrine arose from the decreasing number of \"Visible Saints,\" people who reported conversion experiences. For 10 points, name this reform in Puritan New England which allowed the children of partial church members to be baptized.", "answer": "<b><u>Half-Way</u></b> Covenant", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "<em>In one work, this man states that \u201cassociations of ideas\u201d made in infancy have a more lasting</em> <em>effect than associations made at maturity.</em> While a secretary to the Earl of Shaftsbury, this man created a document which called for laws to expire after 100 years. This author of <em>Some</em> <em>Thoughts Concerning Education</em> and the <em>Fundamental Constitution of Carolina</em> posited that that civil society began with the creation of private property. For 10 points, name this author of the <em>Two Treatises of Government</em>.", "answer": "John <b><u>Locke</u> </b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "<em>A woman named Locusta created these things for Emperor Nero.</em> La Voisin was accused of selling these things in a French affair named for them. Mithridates VI of Pontus was known for consuming small amounts of these things. Lucrezia Borgia allegedly used a ring that contained this sort of thing. During the Black Death, Jews were believed to have put this sort of substance in wells. For 10 points, name this type of substance exemplified by arsenic and cyanide.", "answer": "<b><u>poison</u></b>s [or more specific answers]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This man ordered that public swimming pools be kept cold in the belief it would keep black</em> <em>people away</em>. Fiorello LaGuardia kept a pre-printed pad of resignation letters for this man. He deliberately kept overpasses too low for buses to use the Wantagh Parkway and other roads he built on Long Island. For 10 points, name this subject of Robert Caro\u2019s <em>The Power Broker</em>, who built the Verrazano Narrows Bridge and Cross Bronx Expressway?", "answer": "Robert <b><u>Moses</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>One object used in this practice was known as the terebra.</em> Bart Huges revived modern interest in this technique with the 1964 publication of \"Homo Sapiens Correctus.\" Although in some cultures the roundel created by this process may have served a religious purpose, Paul Broca hypothesized that it was performed to relieve pressure. Hippocrates described this technique in \"On the Injuries of the Head.\" For 10 points, what early method of surgery involved drilling a hole in the patient's skull?", "answer": "<b><u>trepanning</u></b> [or <b><u>trephinning</u></b>; or <b><u>trepanation</u></b>; or <b><u>trephination</u></b>; prompt on descriptive answers mentioning <b><u>drilling</u></b> a hole in the <b><u>skull</u></b> before \"drilling\" is read; do not accept \"craniotomy\"; do not accept \"craniectomy\"]", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This government hired 300 \u201clash bearers.\u201d</em> Lysias escaped from this government, which chose three thousand people to share in their regime. Thrasybulus led a revolt against this regime which culminated at the Battle of Piraeus. One leader of it, Theramenes, was killed on the orders of its most prominent member, Critias, who was tutored by Socrates. For 10 points, name this group of people who were installed as rulers of Athens by Sparta after the Peloponnesian War.", "answer": "<b><u>Thirty</u></b> Tyrants (prompt on \u201cTyrants\u201d)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<em><b><u>In response to one of these events, the Pomgol committee was created by Patriarch Tikhon.</u> </b></em><b><u>An \"unknown\" one of these events was the subject of a Jonathan Dimbleby documentary</u></b> <b><u>that helped cause a 1973 coup. Amartya Sen attributes these events to (+) distribution</u></b> <b>problems in an essay on \"Poverty\" and these events. One of these events in Ethiopia's Wollo province led Bob Geldof to organize the (*) </b>Live Aid concert. Many kulaks died in one of these events possibly aggravated by central planning, called the Holodomor. For 10 points, name this sort of disaster caused by a shortage of food.", "answer": "<b><u>famine</u></b>s [or obvious equivalents like <b><u>starvation</u></b>s]  {III}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>William le Gros distinguished himself in battle during this conflict.</u> </b></em><b><u>A leader in this conflict</u></b> <b><u>escaped Oxford Castle by walking across the frozen River Isis. During this conflict,</u></b> <b><u>Thurstan of York helped crush the forces of David I at the Battle of the Standard. The</u></b> <b><u>Treaty of (+)</u> Wallingford was signed at the end of this conflict, which began after a ship carrying William Adelin sunk near the port of Barfleur. (*)</b> Stephen of Blois took power during this period upon the death of Henry I, subsuming the rightful heiress Empress Matilda. For 10 points, name this period of unrest in early 12th century England.", "answer": "The <b><u>Anarchy</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "CKM"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>For decades, the only English-language biography of this woman was Mary Main's</u> </b></em><b><u>The</u></b> <b><u>Woman with the Whip,</u> </b><em><b><u>which fiercely criticized her.</u></b></em><b><u> This woman began wearing a black</u></b> <b><u>lace gown by Christian Dior in public after a trip in which she was greeted by Francisco</u></b> <b><u>Franco and snubbed by King (+)</u> George VI of Britain. This woman, who was accused of siphoning funds to a Swiss Bank from her namesake charitable \"Foundation,\" went on a (*)</b> \"Rainbow Tour\" of European capitals to raise support for her Justicialist husband. For 10 points, name this first wife and First Lady of Argentine dictator Juan Per\u00f3n.", "answer": "<b><u>E</u></b>va <b><u>Per\u00f3n</u></b> [or <b><u>E</u></b>vita <b><u>Per\u00f3n</u></b>; or Eva <b><u>Duarte</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Discussions of this artwork and of Emily Dickinson bookend and subtitle the aesthetics</u></b></em> <em><b><u>study</u> </b></em><b><u>Sexual Personae</u> </b><em><b><u>by literary critic Camille Paglia.</u> </b></em><b><u>This sculpture has been displayed in</u></b> <b><u>Germany since its 1912 unearthing by Ludwig Borchardt of the German Oriental</u></b> <b><u>Company. The subject of this limestone sculpture, whose left eye is now (+)</u> missing its pupil, wears a flat-topped blue crown indicating her status as a (*) </b>royal wife in Amarna. For 10 points, name this ancient Egyptian sculpture of the head, and chest of the queen of Pharaoh Akhenaten.", "answer": "portrait <b><u>bust</u></b> of <b><u>Nefertiti</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This monarch allied with an English king via the Treaty of Abernathy.</u> </b></em><b><u>A correction made</u></b> <b><u>by Cardinal Placentius prompted this king to snap \"I am the King of the Romans and</u></b> <b><u>above grammar!\" This monarch founded the Order of the Dragon after narrowly escaping</u></b> <b><u>capture when his crusade against (+)</u> Bayezid the Thunderbolt was defeated at Nicopolis. This king called a meeting which ended the Western Schism by electing (*)</b> Martin V, the Council of Constance. For 10 points, name this Holy Roman Emperor from the House of Luxembourg who shared his name with three later kings of Poland.", "answer": "<b><u>Sigismund</u></b> of Luxembourg [or <b><u>Zygmunt</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The melody of this piece\u2019s fifth movement was recycled from its composer\u2019s F</u></b><b><u>\u00eate</u> </b><b><u>des belles</u></b></em> <em><b><u>eaux.</u></b></em><b><u> This piece\u2019s third movement was a solo for Henri Akoka in which the title creatures</u></b> <b><u>are \u201cour desire\u2026 for jubilant Songs,\u201d \u201cAbyss of the birds.\u201d Karl-Albert Br\u00fcll furnished</u></b> <b><u>three of the instruments for this piece\u2019s first performance, and subsequently forged a</u></b> <b><u>stamp out of a potato to help (+)</u> free its performers. \u201cLiturgy of Crystal\u201d opens this 1941 eight-movement work which was composed in the (*) </b>Stalag VIII-A prisoner of war camp. For 10 points, what piece for violin, cello, piano, and clarinet was written by Olivier Messiaen?", "answer": "<em><b><u>Quartet For the End Of Time</u> </b></em>[or <em><b><u>Quatour pour la fin du temps</u></b></em>]  {III}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The Meriam Report severely criticized the implementation of this law</u></b></em><b><u>. Commissioner John</u></b> <b><u>Collier worked to repeal this law, which he believed did not help the people it applied to.</u></b> <b><u>The Burke Act adjusted this law to make it more difficult to become (+)</u> citizens. Henry Teller said this law created \"vagabonds\" in the name of humanity. This law did not apply to many portions of the (*) </b>Oklahoma Territory and it gave 160 acres to a head of an individual family, not tribe. For 10 points, name this pro-assimilation 1887 law that allotted land to American Indians.", "answer": "<b><u>Dawes</u></b> Severalty Act of 1887 [or <b><u>General Allotment</u></b> Act]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>A British operation to reconstruct and analyze these objects was nicknamed Project Big Ben.</u> </b></em><b><u>La Coupole, a site in France, once housed these objects. One of these objects was recovered</u></b> <b><u>from B\u00e4ckebo County in Sweden. A facility producing them was targeted in Operation (+)</u></b> <b>Hydra. These objects, which were primarily designed at the Peenem\u00fcnde Army Research Center by Wernher (*) </b>von Braun, were used against Antwerp and London in the late phases of World War II. For 10 points, name these military projectiles launched by Nazi Germany in conjunction with V-1's.", "answer": "<b><u>V-2</u></b> rockets [or <b><u>Vergeltungswaffe-2</u></b> rockets; or <b><u>A</u></b>ggregat-<b><u>4</u></b>; prompt on just <b><u>rockets</u></b>; do not accept \"V-1 rockets\"]  {III}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The contract that allowed this scandal to occur was signed by Herbert Hoxie.</u> </b></em><b><u>This scandal</u></b> <b><u>broke when Henry Simpson McComb leaked word to the newspaper</u> </b><em><b><u>New York Sun</u></b></em><b><u>.</u></b> <b><u>George Francis Train and Thomas Durant created the company at the center of this</u></b> <b><u>scandal. In this scandal, (+)</u> Oakes Ames handed out shares for the namesake company, which implicated politicians such as James G. (*)</b> Blaine and then-Vice President Schuyler Colfax. For 10 points, name this scandal during Grant's presidency that involved the construction of the Union Pacific Railroad.", "answer": "<b><u>Credit Mobilier</u></b> scandal", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Columbia University's offer to this man of an endowed chair was cancelled due to mass</u></b></em> <em><b><u>student protests</u></b></em><b><u>. This Cabinet member punished a subordinate for writing the Blood</u></b> <b><u>Telegram that questioned \"the suppression of democracy.\" Two members of the Nobel</u></b> <b><u>Committee resigned to protest the awarding of a Peace Prize to this (+)</u> American diplomat for the Paris Peace Accords. Le Duc Tho refused the Nobel he (*)</b> shared with this man for negotiating the Vietnam cease-fire. For 10 points, name this author of <em>On China,</em> a German-born Secretary of State for both Richard Nixon and Gerald Ford.", "answer": "Henry <b><u>Kissinger</u></b> [or Heinz <b><u>Kissinger</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This event's subject proposed that he should be given free meals after finding out that a</u></b></em> <em><b><u>vote\u2019s results were 280 to 220.</u></b></em><b><u> One account of this event includes a digression about the</u></b> <b><u>rendition of Leon of Salamis, and begins with a story about how its subject was told by the</u></b> <b><u>Pythia that there were none (+)</u> wiser than he. Meletus questioned this event's central subject, who compared his city to a sluggish horse and himself to a (*) </b>gadfly. Its subject's defense against accusations of \"corrupting the youth\" is depicted in the <em>Apology</em>. For 10 points, identify this event in which an Athenian philosopher was sentenced to drink hemlock.", "answer": "the <b><u>trial</u></b> of <b><u>Socrates</u></b> [accept Socrates' <b><u>Apology</u></b> until \"<em>Apology</em>\" is read]  {III}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Activist Ray Robinson disappeared during an occupation of this location.</u></b></em><b><u> James W.</u></b> <b><u>Forsyth's men controversially received twenty Medals of Honor for actions at this location.</u></b> <b><u>Marlon Brando's visit to this location led him to refuse his Best Actor Oscar for</u> </b><em><b><u>The (+)</u></b></em> <em><b>Godfather</b></em><b>. It\u2019s not Alcatraz, but in 1973, this location was occupied by members of the American (*)</b> Indian Movement. An earlier incident at this location reacted to the sudden popularity of the Ghost Dance movement. For 10 points, name this location on the Pine Ridge Indian Reservation, where an 1890 massacre of Lakotas took place.", "answer": "<b><u>Wounded Knee</u></b> [accept <b><u>Pine Ridge</u></b> Indian Reservation until it is read]  {III}  <b>Extra Tossup </b> This is a tossup provided for breaking ties or replacing a flubbed or erroneous question at any point in the packet. The power marks are provided so that it may be scored according to fourth quarter rules if it is replacing a fourth quarter question. The power marks should be ignored if this tossup is used to replace a first or second quarter question.", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em><u>T</u><b><u>his province names a type of \"red-slip ware\" pottery which became extremely common</u></b></em> <em><b><u>in the 2</u></b><b>nd</b><b><u> century AD across the Roman Empire.</u></b></em><b><u> The Lesser Syrtis was a gulf in this ancient</u></b> <b><u>province which is now called the Gulf of Gabes. This province's city of Hippo Regius was</u></b> <b><u>eventually presided over by Saint (+)</u> Augustine as a bishop. This province, sometimes denoted with the word \u201cproconsularis\u201d attached was west of (*)</b> Cyrenaica and east of Mauretania. For 10 points, name this province of ancient Rome which contained the ruined Carthage, and now names the whole continent home to Tunisia.", "answer": "<b><u>Africa</u></b> Proconsularis [or Proconsular <b><u>Africa</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}], "bonuses": []}